hello first i'd like to
warmly welcome you to the anna freud
center
to our second series of transformation
seminars
today is the third seminar of the series
we are really delighted that so many of
you are able to join us
these debates are about your questions
about your thoughts about us
collectively developing a new
vision for mental health
we look forward to receiving your
comments and questions
and hope that you all will be inspired
to continue these discussions
after the seminar we're holding these
seminars because
we feel there is an urgent need for a
national discussion
around mental health of children young
people and their families
mental health has become a focus during
the pandemic
and we hope that once we are beyond the
crisis
we will be able to rebuild better for
all of us
also in terms of the mental health of
our young people who are
at the sharpest end of their current
pressures
the theme of the transformation seminars
is thinking differently about mental
health
we invite speakers to respond to a
simple question then ask them
what is their idea to transform
children's and families mental health in
the uk
the seminars explore areas beyond
clinical interventions
important theories are
to ask about how we can
think about do things
differently individually collectively
and as a society to reduce the growing
needs
we have as individuals in our complex
and interconnected social world
and tackle some of the underlying causes
of mental ill health
after the presentation we would like to
invite you to ask questions
you see at the bottom of the screen that
there is a space
for q and a's and if you'd like to
submit your questions we'll try to get
through as many
of them as we can in the time that we
have available
finally if you are tweeting please tag
us
at afn ccf and use the hashtag
transformation seminars
today i am honored and delighted to
welcome
someone who is a world-renowned
exceptional thinker
in his field when i say
his feel it truly is his
because no one has the breadth and depth
of understanding of the human mind
quite like carl frista
carl is a theoretical neuroscientist and
a world authority
on brain imaging and computational
neuroscience
he's one of the most innovative thinkers
about mental health alive today
he's welcome professor of imaging
neuroscience at ucl
he started off in psychiatry but has
been
an independent and extraordinarily
creative thinker applying his own
original photo
his revolutionary impact on studies of
the brain
derives from his inventive use of
probability theory
to analyze neural imaging data
he invented a technique statistical
parametric mapping or
sbm
that is now widely used almost
universally
to look for correspondences in brain
activity
as measured by magnetic resonance
imaging
and cognitive function
he also invented voxel-based morphometry
a sensitive method for measuring
the volume of brain structures one
classical well-known application
demonstrated
the increased volume of a region
underlying spatial memory
and the brains of london taxi drivers
car is dynamic cars dynamic causal
modelling
is used to estimate how different
cortical regions of the brain
influence one another his current
thinking about brain function is
revolutionizing our ideas about
perception
consciousness mental disorder
and the nature of experience itself
the active inference framework
or prediction a minimization
is a relatively recent theory in
mathematical neuroscience
pioneered by carl and his collaborators
it holds considerable promise to be the
unifying theory of the brain
it is used increasingly to support
theoretical predictions in experimental
research
as well as advance the existing theory
of perception and action
my deep admiration for kyle reached new
heights
through reading his contributions to
independence sage or
scientific advisory group for
emergencies
a group of scientists were working
together to provide independent
scientific advice to the uk government
and the property and how to minimize
deaths and support britain's recovery
from the curvy 19 crisis
carl's awards and honours are far too
numerous to mention
i will just pick up a couple
he's a fellow of the royal society
a fellow of the royal society of biology
in 2003 he received
a golden brain award an international
science award in the field of
neuroscience given to people
who made breakthroughs in research on
vision
and the prey in 2013 he was awarded
the international weldon memorial prize
which is bestowed
on the person deemed to have published
the most
noteworthy contribution to the
development of mathematical
or statistical methods applied to
problems in biology
in the previous decade in 2016
he received the charles branch award for
unparalleled breakthroughs in brain
research
and the glass brain award for his
lifetime achievement in the field of
human
brain mapping this evening
we will hear carl discuss the emergence
of selfhood
and how our sense of ourselves
emerges in interaction with the minds
around us
the seminar intriguingly entitled
me and my markov blanket
we are very very privileged to welcome
one of the greatest thinkers in
neuroscience today
welcome carl
thank you very much for that lovely
introduction
it's a true honour and pleasure uh you
know to be with you uh this evening
um i am going to
take the challenge of thinking different
differently
um about mental health very literally
uh to the extent that i feel i should
apologize
for um how different this lecture might
be
from um the kind of lecture that you
would anticipate
um in this series
i'm going to attempt to provide a first
principle account
of dietic interactions and speaking to
selfhood uh as an emergent property of
those interactions
but i'm going to do so from the point of
view of a physicist
so i'm going to present a lecture of two
halves
the first i um again i apologize is
is really a foundational course in the
way things work
the physics of self-organization and i'm
going to lift from that
an understanding of sentience
as an emergent property of
self-organization
so i'm going to talk basically about the
maths
of the mechanics of mind and i'm going
to illustrate
some of the simpler uh principles that
emerge from this treatment
using simulations of primordial soup and
the end point really is a
synchronization between what's on the
inside
and what's on the outside of anything
that exists
um or self-organizes itself to a state
of existence then i'm going to tell
exactly the same
story but using the words
and the language of a clinician or a
neuroscientist
focusing on predictive processing and
predictive coding formulations of how
our brains work
but the end point is exactly the same
it's the
demonstration that the things that
matter
in terms of our engagement with the
world out there
behind our sensorium rests upon a degree
of synchronization
that at the end i'm going to offer as a
metaphor for alignment
um and the thing that glues together
you and me in any dyadic interaction
so that's the the road map um over the
next
few minutes um i normally start the
physics part of this
uh talk with
uh the question posed by scrolling how
can the events in space and time which
take place within the spatial boundary
of a living organism be accounted for by
physics and chemistry
now clearly we're not going to be able
to answer that question but what we can
do
is just focus on the notion of a
boundary of a living organism and of
course
to define anything and specifically a
living organism
you have to define what separates the
organism
from not the organism me from
everything else me from other and
scrolling it would be the first person
to acknowledge that this boundary
is in and of itself a statistical
process
and i'm going to read that boundary um
by borrowing from bayesian mechanics the
notion of a markov blanket
so a markov blanket for those of you who
don't know
is a very simple concept it it's a
statistical
set of states that insulates or
separates
internal states from out external states
on the outside
so graphically we can consider
some little universe here where each of
these circles corresponds to some state
of this universe and the arrows or edges
denote an influence of this state on
that state
and what i can do is i can identify a
set of states here encoded by blue
as internal states and then i can define
the markov blanket or the blanket states
in terms of the parents
the children and the parents of the
children
so that affords a set of states that in
effect
provide all the information i need about
the universe
beyond those states that will enable me
to predict what will happen
on the inside so in other words
statistically speaking
whatever is happening here is
independent of what's happening here
because
given or conditioned upon these blanket
states these blanket states
hold all the information that i need
to tell me about how i'm going to evolve
about my dynamics i'm going to make a
further move here
i'm just going to split bipartition
these blanket states mathematically
into two sets one set which we're going
to call
sensory states that influence but are
not
influenced by the internal states and
another set
active states that are influenced by
internal states but are not influenced
by external states
and with that partition in place i can
now define
the states of any particle or person a
priest
anything that exists as the internal
states
of that particle and their blanket
that comprise the sensory and the active
states and you may be asking
why have i done that um i think the
intuition
is more readily available readily
available if you think about some of
your favorite systems so one of my
favorite systems is the brain
and one can consider the internal states
of the brain as
every state of synaptic activity
efficacy
connectivity that constitutes a
particular
internal state of the brain and these
internal states in your activity
are communicated or influence active
states my actuators
my autonomic nervous system that
produces changes
in the external states out there the
physiological states of my body
or the motor states of my um my
uh motor plant that change
the sensations the sensory states that
are
picked up and impinge upon my internal
states so that i have this of circular
causality
where the internal states exchange for
the external states
through the markov blanket a dual uh
carriageway where the influence of the
in the inside on the outside is mediated
by the active states and the influence
of the outside on the inside
is mediated by the sensory states and
these
arrows are what license my
attribution of states to internal or
external sentencery
or active in the sense that they denote
the conditional independences that we've
uh just described that define the markov
blanket
but this structure can be found anywhere
that you can separate something from the
rest of the universe so
for example a little cell will have
intra internal states will correspond to
the intracellular states the
active states could be the actin
filaments that support the surface
states that push the surface states into
the
external milia the external states that
reciprocate by changing the
cell surface sensory receptors that
cause changes in the internal states and
so
this perception action cycle at this
very elemental level
is still in play and rests upon
this markovian partition into
internal external and intervening
blanket states
so what i want you to do now is to bear
that in mind
but forget about it for the moment what
we're going to do next is just to
consider
the physics of systems that
self-organize
and then what we're going to do is to
put the markov blanket
back in play and see what implications
it has for the relationship between
what's on the inside
and what's on the outside so
this is a bit heavy again i apologize
for
the mathematics you don't need to
understand the functional form of these
equations
but but i think they are useful just to
sketch the
architecture of the ideas and in fact um
if you are mathematically minded
that their simplicity so what i've done
here
is just drawn the kind of universe
that i'm interested in and i'm
interested in
universes that exist that persist over
time
so mathematically that means that they
have an attracting set
um another word for that is that they
constitute a random dynamical system
with a global random attractor so
more intuitively i've just sketched out
two states here it could be
the temperature of my body
some say the concentration of oxygen
if i was a physiologist and i've traced
out
over time the way that these states
might
change this could stand in for anything
it could be
very fast fluctuations and electrical
and chemical
constituents of a part of my brain
unfold over milliseconds to give me uh
synchronized activity in the brain it
could be my heartbeat two aspects of my
heart contracting
every second or so it could be me
getting up in the morning
having a cup of coffee doing my emails
looking forward to lunch
it could be christmas easter some
holidays birthday this structure has to
exist at any scale
at any spatial and temporal scale
crucially embodying the fact
that its existence depends upon
revisiting the same
states the neighborhood of the same
states time and time again
after a suitable period of time so these
are the states x they
change according some flow here with
some random perturbations of
fluctuations denoted by
omega here now the reason i've gone to
some length in just
casting the mathematical basis of the
arguments
in terms of the flow of dynamical
systems
is a well-established and ger very
ubiquitous
formulation of the behavior of these
kinds of systems
that inherits from the fact that if i
keep revisiting the same states
then i can treat this attracting set of
states that i keep revisiting that
characterize me or things like me
in terms of a probability distribution
that you will find me in this state
if you sample me any random time and i
can write down the mathematics
of the way that this probability
distribution itself
evolves but we've just said it doesn't
change with time because we exist over
time
so what we can do is we can solve um the
equation describing
the density dynamics it's called the
punk equation you may
know it or you may not as uh the
scrotinger equation or the master
equation
effectively all the same things the
solution to that the particular solution
for things that exist over time
is remarkable in the following sense
using
a particular decomposition the helmholtz
decomposition
it tells me immediately that things that
exist
will flow in a way that can be described
as a gradient flow on the log
probability
of being in any particular state
um i'm going to give you some intuition
as to how this equation unpacks because
i think it's quite interesting
but also just to illustrate its
simplicity what we're basically saying
is that well let's imagine that i placed
a drop of oil
in some water or on say a sheet
of blotting paper now the kinds of
systems that dissipate that we're not
interested in that don't self-assemble
and don't have this attracting set of
characteristic states they would behave
a little bit like this
the ink molecules would diffuse
throughout the solvent
until they dispersed everywhere subject
to the random molecular
uh fluctuations the systems that we're
talking about
usually living systems behave very
differently
they appear to gather themselves up
and assemble in a restricted number of
states or places that they could be in
other words it looks as if
their states are flowing up
concentration gradients
resisting or offsetting the random
fluctuations that will be
dispersing them and that's all that this
equation says it just says that
any system that exists can be described
in terms of its dynamics its
flow its movement its evolution and that
that
flow can be decomposed into two
components
there's the part that gathers things up
that resists the entropic erosion and
dispersion dissipation decay
dilution that is
this component here that's more
proportional to the amplitude of those
random fluctuations gamma
and then there's another component
that's right angles to that that
circulates on the iso probability
contours it's called solenoidal
flow and this is denoted by the q here
so
anything that exists can be written down
in terms of its dynamics in terms of
this decomposition
into a gradient flow that flows up the
concentration
variance and this circular or solenoidal
flow
and you'll all be familiar with this
very ubiquitous description of dynamics
when you're looking at water flowing
down the plug hole
so the gradient flow is going downhill
and the circular flow
is the swirling around uh that one
witnesses
so that's how things that exist
behave dynamically what about the markov
blanket
well what is true of all the states is
true
of the active and the internal states
so at the same time that the internal
states
look as if they're performing a gradient
flow on the log probability of the
blanket states
it is also the case that the active
states are doing the same
and i'm going to offer this as a
mathematical
image of perception changing
our internal states and action changing
our active states but in the service of
looking as if we're increasing the same
quantity and that quantity is this log
probability of the blanket states
so what does that mean well it's
probably something that you're very
familiar with depending upon
um your commitments academically or the
way that you understand
optimization processes i've just listed
a few things here
and i uh and in the hope that you will
recognize
you know at least one if not if not all
of them the first interpretation of this
quantity here this log
of the probability of my blanket states
being characteristic of the kind of
thing i am
me or my markov blanket
we can interpret this as simply an
expression of value these are the
states that i aspire to that i am
generally found in
um mathematically we can approximate
this quantity with a con
with something known as a a free energy
or an
evidence lower bound in machine learning
but the the
perspective i'm selling in this
interpretation
is that all systems that exist will look
as if they are
performing a gradient flow on this value
function
and of course this is exactly the
assumption
the foundation of reinforcement learning
optimal control theory
and economics expected utility theory
so that's one perspective an equivalent
complementary perspective is on the
negative
value so if you did information theory
this would be known as self
information or surprisal or more simply
surprise
the negative log probability the
improbability of finding my
blanket states in this state here which
means that we can
construe the self-organization of
internal active states in terms of a
suppression
of surprise and this leads to things
like the infomax principle
uh the minimum redundancy principle and
indeed the the free energy principle
that's nice because the time average of
surprise
is mathematically called entropy which
means it looks as if
or it will any system that exists
will look as if it's trying to minimize
its entropy
so this clearly is the holy grail of
synergetics that tries to understand the
imperatives behind self-organization
and if you're a physiologist it's just
homeostasis it's just
gathering your physiological states
within bounds
to preclude uh an entropic dispersion
and wandering into non-viable or highly
surprising
physiological states i'm going to
pursue another interpretation and which
is more
statistical in nature inferential in
nature and
in statistics and in particular bayesian
statistics the probability
of the blanket states given a markov
blanket or given me
can also be interpreted as something
called model evidence or marginal
likelihood
bayesian model evidence so this is
basically saying
the states the internal active states
are changing in a way that appears to be
maximizing
model evidence and that finds a nice
home
uh when unpacked in terms of the
bayesian brain hypothesis
evidence accumulation and as we've heard
an introduction
uh things like predictive coding
so if it's the case that anything that
exists
should look as if it was doing some sort
of prediction or modeling
of what's beyond its markov blanket
then we should be able to simulate that
and show its emergence in any
um any self-organizing system that
possesses
a markov blanket so what i'm going to do
is
briefly show you some simulations of a
little universe that we've engineered
precisely to show and or to ask the
question can we
convince this kind of mechanics this
kind
of synchronization between the inside
and the outside that's what we've done
here
is just built a little world comprised
of 128
macromolecules uh the details not
important the same
phenomena emerge irrespective of the
differential equations
one uses all we need to know is that
they're all loosely coupled
um and we can see them bubbling away to
um
at the bottom of a potential well here
and you may be asking well why have i
done this
what are we going to do next well
because we've written down
the equations of motion that underwrite
the flow that we've been talking about
we know what influences what we know
which molecules
synthetic molecules influence which
other synthetic molecules
and we can preclude action resistance
and
in virtue of that we can now define
the conditional dependencies that define
the markov blanket
so the hope was that we'll be able to
find a little creature living in this
synthetic primordial soup defined purely
on the basis of its markov blankets the
parents the children
and the parents of the children defined
by this adjacency matrix and
here indeed is a little viral-like
particle wiggling around in the middle
of the synthetic soupy
little cilium or tail here where the
internal states
have been color-coded with blue the
active states that typically in these
simple simulations
usually underlie the um sensory states
in the magenta here
pushing them into the external states
external media
in cyan here so this simulation
reveals that there is indeed a little
creature living in the middle of this
soup
that's quite happily attaining and
maintaining
its visiting its attracting sets
its technically non-equilibrium steady
state
but the question now is can we find any
evidence that the
internal states are somehow maximizing
the evidence for some implicit model of
what's going on on the outside in other
words do
internal states appear to infer the
causes
of their sensory states some people in
philosophy like to call this
self-evidencing soliciting
evidence for your own existence um
and it's relatively easy to demonstrate
that
indeed this process is manifest
um this example here is used
to illustrate the simulation of
synthetic event related potentials used
in
cognitive neuroscience and
electrophysiology but just to quickly
walk you through it because what i want
to get to is this
underlying construct called a
synchronization manifold
what we've done here is ask are there
any mixtures of the internal states
that will predict the motion of the
external states
so this is a little bit like asking are
there any patterns of neuronal activity
in the visual brain that accompany
motion visual motion outside that is
registered
by our sensory epithelia
and indeed it is easy to find this this
has to exist
and i'll explain why in a second and
here is an illustration so
what we've done here is take a mixture
of motions
fluxes of the external states um
shown in cyan the prediction of those
and the
90 confidence intervals based just upon
the internal states remembering that the
internal states can't see
the external states all they know is
what they um
how the external states impress
themselves on the sensory states
and uh and the influence of the sensor
states by the active states on the
internal states
and we can see there's a remarkable
correspondence between
the implicit knowledge the inference
predicated on the internal fluctuations
um about what's going on on the outside
despite the fact that there is no direct
access and indeed if we gather together
little excursions here
and average them we can uh simulate um
um event related potentials here's an
empirical example from monkey
electrophysiology
so you may be asking well how does this
happen why why is it the case
well it must be the case in the sense
that for any given blanket state
there must be an average internal state
and an
average external state which means there
must exist
um for any given blanket state
the expected internal mode of activity
and an external mode of activity and all
we're seeing is
fluctuations on this synchronization
manifold
and i'm using the word synchronization
manifold just to bring to closure that
you know the first half of this talk
with a nod to what has been understood
for centuries and in particular uh the
notion of
generalized synchronization or
synchronization of chaos
uh noted by christian huygens um many
many years ago
and most of you will be familiar with
this is the
observation that suspend two clocks from
the same wall
or beam and inevitably after a period of
time
they will start to oscillate in
synchrony
they will become entrapment
they were becoming aligned it can there
is no other solution and this is
basically just an illustration
of this fundamental property of uh
couple dynamical systems in this
instance we're coupling the inside to
the outside precariously through the
blanket states
so here's actually a drawing um by
hogan's
um with two clocks suspended from the
same beam so from our point of view
um one clock or one pendulum can be
the internal states and the other can be
the external states
and they are coupled through the beam uh
in terms of the blankets debates
comprising the active and the sensory
states
so i like this construct because it um
it illustrates
the complete symmetry here so if you
subscribe to this interpretation
of synchronization where the inside
is trying to you are trying to infer
what's going on in the world
then you also have to accept that the
world is trying to infer what you're
about and what you're doing
and that's not announced a non sensible
uh interpretation when it comes to
things like niche construction and the
like
however um we are going to um
try to get back to this notion of
synchronization
through another route but let me just
first of all summarize what we've done
uh with all the heavy lifting in terms
of the physics
what we're saying is that the existence
of a particle or a person
anything that exists implies a partition
of a systems state systemic states into
internal
blanket namely sensory active and
external states that are hidden behind
the markov blanket and because active
states change
but are not changed by external states
they're going to reduce
the average surprise or the entropy of
blanket states and this means that
action will appear to maintain the
structural and functional integrity
of the blanket and some people like to
discuss this in terms of
self-assembly in chemistry or in the
life sciences autophages
internal states appear to infer the
hidden causes of sensory states by
increasing
their bayesian model evidence
namely self-evidencing and actively
influence those causes
via what is often called in my world
active inference just one little twist
here for
philosophers um there is an argument
that
the internal states in virtue of the
existence of the synchronization
manifold parameterize probabilistic
beliefs about
external states and one can unpack that
in terms of
information geometry and complement a
cartesian dualism
with a markovian monism but we're not
telling that story today um what we oh
so yes this is just a little interlude
um this is
um one of my post docs um went to
america to work with mike levin
at tufts and a few months after arriving
um he and his wife had a little baby and
his wife
bought him uh a mark off blanket so here
is
um keira the little baby with um franz's
markov blanket here's markov blanket so
if you
mark off so if you if you want a mark of
blanket they are available
in america so we've done the statistics
of life
and what i promised i would do now
is just rehearse exactly the same story
but from the point of view of a
neuroscientist
trying to understand sentience and how
we make sense of the world um
so i'm going to unpack this part of the
talk in terms of the basics the
fundamentals of the anatomy of inference
in terms of predictive
coding um with a brief focus on clinical
micro circuits and in particular sensory
attenuation because i think that's
a particularly important aspect of
the physics of sentience particularly in
psychiatry
and indeed mental health and then
conclude with an illustration of all
this in action
and my font hope is to get back to
synchronization
and what it means for models of the
world
where the world includes other things
like me
and indeed could include me um
so the anatomy of inference all of this
is predicated on the underlying notion
that can be traced back to the students
of plato i think most
best articulated by helmholtz as we see
it
seen a moment the notion that
perception rests upon
a constructive act and it's a
perspective on perception which is
in contrast to 20th century sort of
outside
in filtering sensory information it
rests upon an
inside out constructive act where you
construct predictions or hypotheses
that best explain the signals and
sensations of your sensory states of
your sensory epithelium
so you have to have something in mind as
a potential explanation
for your sensations before you can
perceive it
i think this is beautifully illustrated
by
the this painter famed for doing still
life oils
that when viewed from a different
perspective
give you a very different percept so if
previously you saw a bowl of fruit
and now you see a face the key thing is
you brought that face to the table that
is your explanation
it's this inside out act that now
enables you to find a better explanation
a simple explanation for why you're
perceiving or sensing this particular
pattern of
sensory signals
so helmholtz would i think in the
science and the life sciences and the
physical sciences be
the person who first articulated this
most clearly nicely illustrated by this
sentence or quote here objects are
always imagined as being present
in the field of vision as would have to
be there in order to produce
the same impression on the nervous
mechanism so again speaking to the
notion
that it is um the impressions you get
on the sensory epithelia are
are explained by what would happen if
this was the cause and the cause has to
be imagined
in a mindful way and clearly this is
very much
akin to richard gregory
uh and other um seminal
psychologists of the 20th century who
formulated
perception as a hypothesis testing again
this notion that
using sensory evidence sensations
sensory states
as evidence for or against a perceptual
explanation or hypothesis and if
confirmed
then you commit to that and that is what
you see
um as opposed to what you are looking at
these ideas have been used to great
effect in a technical
uh arena um particularly machine
learning by people like
geoffrey hinton and in a slightly more
translational
setting by people like uh peter diane
and indeed
they came up with the notion of a
helmholtz machine
as a machine learning or neural network
formulation of this basic idea
borrowing ideas from thomas bayes and in
particular richard feynman's
free energy or variational solution to
the problem
of this difficult inference problem that
we all face
when finding the best explanations for
our sensorium
um let's just go back to
helmholtz producing impressions
on the nervous system so this fits very
nicely with this
markovian blanket construct so what
we're talking about here is
if it is the case that to to it to be
is to perform gradient flows on
evidence model evidence what i am
effectively saying is
i will appear to try and explain
the best explanation or causes
for the sensory impressions or the
shadows
on my sensory states my sensory veil so
i will be trying to
discern or represent what is causing
these sensory shadows here
and using this the maths that i
presented in the first
half um one can sketch out how
our brains actually do this in a
relatively straightforward way
um so these equations again may look
complicated but
you know once you get used to them they
are remarkably simple
and yet may explain
how our brains and our neuronal message
passing
actually implement this fantastic act
of being able to explain what's causing
our sensorium
to produce those fantasies um that are
vertically endorsed by the sensory uh
this are sensory
evidence that we you know we gather with
our eyes and our ears and
all other organs so let's just come back
to this gradient flow
and focus on the internal states so
here's our gradient flow
on this log probability under some
simplifying assumptions gaussian
assumptions we can write this
expression in this form here which is a
mixture of two things
the rate of change my internal state say
my neuronal activity
can be broken into the solenoidal part
which is
in engineering known as a prediction so
it's a particular one i would
the states of the world in the future
without any observing any new
information
so nothing is actually changing in terms
of the underlying surprise because it's
a prediction
about things i haven't yet seen and then
a prediction error
epsilon which is the difference between
what i predicted
and what i actually and
this gradient flow basically is just
saying
we're going to minimize the sum squared
error weighted by that precision pi here
so just to try and give you an intuition
of what that
sort of how that would work um in
a sort of uh coarse-grained fashion
let's imagine that we have this sensory
impression here this
shadow on our sensory epithelia and we
had some expectation
or mean explanation mu here
that the best explanation was of a
howling dog
and if i had a generative model g that
could generate from this expectation
what i would have seen my sensory states
that would have been produced if this
was right
then i could compare the prediction
generated by the generative model
with the actual sensations and elaborate
a prediction error
and then i can simply use my prediction
error to
optimize or change my expectations until
the prediction error
has been minimized and at which point i
will have a perfectly good
explanation for my sensory impressions
and that changing that beijing belief
updating that evidence accumulation
is just this gradient flow it's just
minimizing prediction error
um notice that the name of the game here
is to minimize prediction error or to
maximize the the
probability of the sensory or the
blanket states under a particular model
of the world that is generating the
predictions
we'll never actually know what caused
these sensations
but that's not the point if i can get
through my life
minimizing prediction error job done and
of course that job is done by this
gradient flow
um up here so this provides
a nice and parsimonious very simple
picture
um of active sentience um
so we can forget about all the focal
point equations and the gradient flows
and we can say that we can explain
everything
in terms of minimizing prediction error
which means that we can understand
perception as
the changing of internal for example
brain states
to supply predictions that are as close
as possible to the sensations and that
would be
a canonical way of minimizing prediction
error and we can regard that as
perception changing predictions however
there is another
way of minimizing prediction error we
could actually go
and resample our sensory states
our sensations to make them more like
the predictions
and this involves actively new
sensations from the environment by
looking over there or by touching this
or touching that and that gives a nice
explanation
for changing sensations to minimize
prediction error
so both action and perception are simply
there in the service
of minimizing prediction error um
so what would that look like in a little
brain and i've deliberately chosen
a bird brain here because i want to use
um
birdsong uh as a little simulation at
the end
just to illustrate and make concrete
some of the
phenomena that we've been talking about
so
imagine this is um a piece of neural
anatomy from
a bird brain this is the auditory
thalamus of a songbird
it receives some sensations so let's
assume that the bird is currently
listening to
for something it receives these
fluctuating
um sonogram representations of sensory
input
time frequency and in the absence of any
top-down
predictions there is the sensations just
to become
the prediction error they go up to the
higher vocal center
for example where they drive through
this gradient flow
expectations have tried to provide
predictions of what's coming in
until such point as the predictions
match the input
and the prediction error is quenched or
resolved
however at the same time while these
first order predictions are fluctuating
being driven by the ascending prediction
errors
they are also in receipt of top-down
predictions from a higher area
say area x in the in the songbirds brain
uh and the same mechanics ensues that
there's a difference between
the activity here and the top-down
prediction that elaborates a prediction
and sent forward
to get better top-down predictions of
the first order
predictions that generate um and try to
suppress the first order prediction
errors and you can see how you can build
this hierarchy into
a deep generative model uh of the sort
necessary
for inferring what's going to happen
next at different temple scales
a narrative or in this instance uh bird
song
this is a useful explanation for
listening
but notice that we've also included in
the things
the sensations that have to be predicted
the sensations
that are reporting the status of my
motor plant in this instance the
um the voice box of the bird
here so the if i
were able to if i was listening then i
would uh
i would not be uh predicting any
sensations from
for my articulatory muscles any stretch
receptor signals however i can use
exactly the same generative model
same machinery predictive machinery
to actually reproduce and sing
and all i need to do is basically switch
on
by increasing the precision uh or
of the descending predictions of
what i would feel if i was actually
producing this
sensory input and then i would have
a difference between my top down
predictions and what i'm actually
sensing from my muscles
and i would have a prediction error and
i could use that prediction error to
drive
my expectations and in fact i wasn't
singing or
i can send them back outside to the
world and actually cause the muscles to
move
until they supply the predicted signals
so all i've done here is sketch a
computational anatomy that is isomorphic
exactly the same
as a classical reflex arc where the way
that we move
and indeed the way that we secrete in
terms of autonomic
action is rests upon top down
predictions
providing a set point for classical
reflex arcs that these peripheral
prediction errors actually drive
and fulfill and all this requires is a
sort of yin yang or a selective gating
of whether i am attending to
switching on the precision of the
prediction errors
pertaining to proprioception to action
or extra reception in this instance
auditory
um sensations so this
illustrates a very important role of um
of precision in contextualizing whether
i'm
passively listening and not moving or
whether i'm actually generating the
sensations
actively and implicitly
also attenuating the consequences of my
own action
sometimes referred to as sensory
attenuation
technically what we are the story that
we've just told
this little predictive coding with
reflexes formulation of active inference
is a story about the top-down
predictions descending predictions
playing the role of coral redischarge
predicting
stuff that i'm sensing in the extra
receptive domain
and at the same time bilaterally
generating predictions of proprioception
that are interpreted as motor commands
by the
peripheral nervous system and my
neuromuscular
junctions from the point of view of the
control of precision this is often this
mechanism
sort of switching between sensory
attenuation
and sensory attenuation sensory
attention
and selection uh sometimes interpreted
in terms
of um attention
being if you like the psychological
homolog of this sort of precision
engineered
message passing here i just want to
drill down on that because i'm going to
use that
in the final couple of slides um to
simulate the attic interactions um so
just to show you
how potent this precision modulation
of the prediction errors that we're
trying to uh
that we use to select the kinds of
prediction errors that we want to
minimize on that we believe
convey precise information for our
belief updating
i'm going to play a little game if you
allow me to play this game
um it's illustrative of
one of the clearest examples
of um sensory attenuation
which is called circadic suppression but
i'll explain how and why
just after illustrating its potency so
this is not going to work very well
given that you're all very remote but
could you if you are a man
do one task and if you're a woman do
another task and the task is as follows
in a moment sherlock holmes is going to
jump from this side of the screen
to the other side of the screen and your
job
is to tell me whether any aspect
of this picture of sherlock holmes
changed
when it goes from here to here
i'd like the women to
focus on this fixation point here in the
center
so they have to keep their eyes still
and um tell me whether sherlock holmes
changed on pass on
whilst fixating on the cross conversely
the men i'd like you to focus on shark
homes and try and track sherlock holmes
and what i want to know is who's the
best at being able to detect
whether or not anything changed
uh in the um picture of
sherlock holmes so if you if you can all
do that
i'm going to pick on um lydia as
representative of women to give
to give me her answer and tim as
representative
of men to give me uh give me um
the uh given the men's answer so lydia
and tim can you can you focus
if you're still there on on this little
particular little task right so three
two one
and then it's going to jump three two
one
lydia can you hear me hi
yes i can what did you did you think
sherlock holmes changed in
any aspect well i saw something
flat up in the middle oh
what did you see i think it said did you
miss me
okay that's tim okay
okay tim are you there i'm there i'm
here yes
i'm afraid i didn't see anything
i didn't no you didn't see anything at
all
no change jonah combs
so beautiful that that is a lovely
illustration
of the power of psychotic suppression or
sensitive attenuation
um um in the oculomotor context
so what lydia well done that was you
only had about 50 milliseconds to see
that but you did indeed see did you miss
lee
and and the idea here is the reason that
you lydia saw this
um was that you were not suppressing the
precision of your visual prediction
errors
because you weren't moving tim on the
other hand
had to suppress the prediction the
visual prediction errors because they
were a consequence of its active
sensing or visual palpation of the world
so this is a lovely example of enforced
sensory attenuation where we're
basically transiently blind
or transiently suspend our attention
when we cause the sensations and of
course when we move our eyes
there is an enormous visual flow or
optic flow
induced simply by our eye movements
which we cannot see
and in virtue of the fact that tim could
not see it whilst he was moving his eyes
he couldn't see anything else
either which is why you lydia were the
only person that
could actually see the digi did you miss
me
so i think this is a wonderful example
of you know hardwired
sensory attenuation that really has a
profound influence of
on on how the sensorium
updates our belief and how that depends
exquisitely
on agency and action and what i want to
do now is just to close
by leveraging um
sensory attenuation and augmentation
that underwrites
whether i'm whether i'm listening or
talking or whether i'm
um listening or singing to
simulate now um daddick interactions so
previously we've been talking
and simulating little creatures um
into exchanging with the external world
what i'm doing now was making a further
move
and putting two markov blankets um face
to face as it were
so the internal states of one blanket
are the external states of another
blanket
in the hope of simulating dyadic
interactions
but to do that to preserve the
conditional independences
i have to do turn taking and i'm going
to use this precision
mechanism to turn take so one in this
instance is going to be a bird is
listening
and then it's singing and then it's
listening and then it's singing
and vice versa for the other bird so
when we um integrate those equations
and just let the birds sing and when we
integrate those
equations of motion that predictive
coding equation with the prediction and
the
uh gradient uh the prediction of
minimization part
of a neuro of a neurobiologically um
plausible sword
for the generative model that i've just
described
for singing and listening we can
simulate
what would happen if two birds were
singing in the same locale
what i've done here is separate the two
birds
so that they can't hear each other
so what you're listening to now is what
one bird
is actually hearing it can't hear itself
so it can hear itself but it can't hear
the other bird
and they're now simply going to repeat
the simulation
but bringing the two birds within
hearing range of each other
so now they can hear each other
and then i'm going to track the internal
states at different levels in this
synthetic cortical hierarchy that are
providing
the predictions and the prediction
errors for
the song that you've just heard
and now if we listen to what is
perceived by
the first bird you can now hear a
continuous
melody and this melody is composed of
itself singing and then hearing the
other bird then itself
and the other bird and in contrast to
the previous slide
what we're seeing here is a
synchronization
and this synchronization ensues because
both birds have the same generative
model
they both have the same beliefs about
what's out there
and in this instance what's out there is
exactly the same
as itself which means that this is a
really powerful way to minimize surprise
or prediction error in the sense that
if you are like me and we are in
exchange
then you become very predictable from my
point of view because
anything that i do you are doing and
vice versa and this holds for you as
well
so dadically altogether we can now
minimize
our free energy or minimize our
prediction error simply because where
we are committing to the same narrative
to the same sensory states and active
states
that generate the sensorium and our
sensorium is shared
and it's mutually predictable simply
because i can assume that you are like
me
and under that assumption and
when two things are sufficiently similar
and they can learn
mutually to be sufficiently similar then
we see the emergence
again of the synchronization manifold so
here in a different context but it's
mathematically exactly the same
construct that we um
that we looked at with the simulations
the primordial soup what i've done is
trapped out the new brain activity if
you like the neural activity generating
predictions
when the two birds couldn't hear each
other at the different levels in this
synthetic cortical hierarchy and then
exactly the same
neural activity patterns when they can
hear each other
just to show you how they align how they
become
synchronized of course we now know that
they it couldn't be in any it couldn't
be in any other way
um in the sense that these uh
this is the kind of coupling that is
the non-equilibrium steady state or it
is
this attracting set of states that must
emerge very much like huygens clocks
so that's an illustration of
synchronization in terms of
communication and this is a very
elemental communication
literally singing from the same hints
sheet in order to be able
to infer a very elemental if you like
theory of mind
the the last slide
is really an invitation to think about
what that means
for the way that we learn our genitive
models of the world
to exploit this free energy minima
this this prediction error solution
in a world that is populated constitute
constitutes creatures like me i can
assume that every creature like me is
like me
and we're all seeing from the same hem
sheet but to get there
i have to learn that the world out there
comprises creatures like me so
here is the challenge for a newborn
first of all the newborn has to
distinguish between
the things that it can act upon and the
things that he has no control over
in order just to develop a sense a
generative model
that enables it to recognize those
reflexes and parts of the world can be
controlled
and can't be controlled but the even
greater challenge then
is to recognize and to learn
by this surprise minimizing free energy
minimizing prediction error
mechanism applied to the connections and
the structure and the parameters of the
generative model
to learn that the best explanation for
its sensorium is a fact that many of the
sensations are supplied by something
else
another and in particular a mother
that is something like me which would be
the final
uh the final stage a very elemental
um sort of um simplistic sense
of learning that there are
things like me out there so
having developed a sense of mother then
one might suppose that that a neonate
might test then the hypothesis or
perhaps
i am like mother and thereby leading to
a sense of self so in a rather cursory
way
i've managed to get to the um what was
promised in the introduction
um from peter about agency
and a sense of self but in a way really
which is more an invitation
um to interpret and discuss uh whether
the underlying
physics of sentience really makes sense
in terms of speaking to these
fundamental questions um about selfhood
and
relationships with others um
i'll end with a quote from fireman it's
usually a technical quote but i thought
this would be more
appropriate in the given in the current
context the highest forms of
understanding
we can achieve our laughter and human
compassion and with that
it just remains for me to thank um all
the people whose ideas i've been talking
about
and most importantly thank you for your
attention thank you very much indeed
and i'm going to pass now back to peter
thank you thank you so much carl
i've been monitoring some of the
comments
in between and if i could just cite to
you a few
enlightening lecture thank you
this is so interesting and brilliantly
explained so
i've got some questions but just uh to
say
um in
kind of try and do a little bit of
translation
what is remarkable about your um
view is really that it's it's like the
picture that you should you've turned
uh perception uh upside down in the kind
of active inference framework
um that there is um
that the traditional notion of
perception
uh uh and action and everything between
is not a kind of the end point of a
whole long line of processing but
really something that we generate from
inside
[Music]
and then compare without there now those
of us here
working clinically and a number of
questions from that perspective
have known this all along uh we have
been
you're not telling us anything new
you've known this that that people
just interpret their world and you know
they try and minimize prediction error
and they change the world until the
prediction error is minimized
and
and some of that uh has very painful
consequences
in some ways it has distressing
consequences in psychopathology
and one of the questions and there'll be
more technical questions one of the
questions that
people really want you to address just a
little bit because i know that you have
done
uh is how
would you brilliant though your your
model is
um how how would you um
see uh mental disorder how would you see
psychopathologies
in terms of prediction error and
does it is there a risk uh which i don't
think there is but
but i think we could do with the
reassurance that is there a risk that
some sort of innate disruption in
uh minimizing prediction errors could
be at the root of
mental disorder or is that a consequence
of
historical experience in terms of a
consequence of uh
personal experience over to you carl
excellent question um so just speaking
to this sort of
you know turning things on their head it
is i think
a nice example of what uh dan denick
calls a strange inversion
but clearly not strange to you and
people actually work with with
with people um but for some um
people in machine learning and
artificial intelligence it's certainly a
strange inversion but much more natural
for people to work with
actually also real artifacts of
artificial sort in robotics
but the the deeper i think more
challenging question which i'm sure
we'll drill down to is you know
where does this mechanics um
yield some interesting um hypotheses
about
false inference and the uh competent
behaviors that attend
or belief states that attend false
inference that we see
um in
psychopathology of its various flavors
and i think you've you you've carved up
the answer
into two domains already which is part
of it is this
false inference in the moment what leads
what's what's the
um the first principle account of a
false belief
or indeed a false percept um
and um in the moment and then there's
the other
um questions which are more about the
learning of the generative models
so there's the deployment of a
generative model inverted
in the moment given the sensory evidence
given all the evidence from your
interception from your pro-social
interactions
at hand to use your genitive model to
infer what's going on at the moment
and you know how i can sample or create
new information to make
my predictions come true as opposed to
in a developmental or indeed actually in
any experience dependent
setting the um the updating of
the parameters the contingencies the
lawful aspects the structure of that
genetic model
that would underwrite you know the
emergence of a sense of agency
attachment uh possibly a description of
you know the um development of a daddy
relationship over
over you know days months weeks and
years
so in in the first domain
um there's a really practical answer and
it just comes from the empiricism
um that um um you know
one can find in academic psychiatry and
academic neurology
when one looks at the the process
theories and neuronal process theories
that mediate this gradient flow then it
seems that the
both the um the nature of false
inference the psychopathology if you
like
and the neurophysiology almost
universally identifies a failure of that
precision
so it's a failure of that sensory
attenuation that we were illustrating
with the um psychedelic suppression but
at a much higher level
so whether you're talking about
parkinson's disease
failure to um attenuate proprioceptive
information that i'm not moving i'm
therefore
never being able to develop the fantasy
that i'm moving
leading to psycho psychomotor poverty or
whether
it's the hallucinosis of organic
psychosyndromes
or indeed schizophrenia where
you um or perhaps the poster child here
would be autism
um where you are unable
to modulate or attenuate the precision
afforded sensory evidence so you become
glued to the sensorium
you fail to develop deep centrally
coherent genitive models of your world
you cannot disattend
nothing is surprising because nothing
uh ev everything is is worthwhile
predicting so you can't
have illusions you can't have mismatched
negativities or ball responses
all cardinal signs of you know of things
like schizophrenia
so you put that failure of sensory
attenuation in a developmental context
and just ask what it must be like
to be born into a world that you're
trying to make sense of
you know and all your sensing is
possibly a rattle or
suckling uh or nurturing behavior or
fillative touch from your mother
and you're trying to make sense of the
world but you can't disattend
from anything to actually drill down and
start to build a deep model
that provides a passiveness explanation
of the kind ah
mother is a creature she is an object
out there
that's doing stuff to me i cause this
bit and she calls that mid
so you know then the game gets
exquisitely difficult
um in terms of understanding the
profound implications of
a failure to suspend your attention
in a in an apt way to
realize your agency or
disambiguate i cause that or you caused
that
there is a finding that um
originally uh john watson brought
forward to the developmental world that
babies up to the age of about three
months uh
and attend uh
with preference things that are
perfectly contingent with their actions
after three months they prefer to attend
to things that are
clearly but uh clearly not perfectly
contingent
nearly contingent but not perfectly
contingent and that
autistic children do not have
this switch at the three-month switch
would this be consistent with what
you're suggesting
yes it would i didn't know that's
fascinating i mean you know if i if i
had to build
um a baby in silicon that's exactly what
one would hope would happen in the
normal development
you've got to learn what bits of this
world um you know can i
act upon and what bits can't you know
that's that that's the first thing that
you need to do to just the
self-discovery
without any sense of selfhood per se but
then you get to the more interesting
bits
well you know i thought i could control
this but perhaps there's another agents
out there
and then you start to you know get it
find that much more epistemically
uh attractive it has much more epistemic
affordance these things i thought i
could
control but in fact someone else might
be out there
let me try and uh squeeze another
question
so enlightening lecture thank you
i'm a psychologist working with parents
who struggle to relate to their kids who
engage
in very high risk behaviors part of the
issue is that often parents
overreact emotionally feeding into the
behavior staying calm and
acting counteractively is a challenge so
thinking about the mark of blanket model
where would you start with these parents
not an easy question it's no because i
i was immediately trying to answer it as
a psychiatrist
you're a physicist as a mathematician um
as a mathematician all this very
simple-minded um
treatment of dyadic interactions brings
to the table
is the um the notion of generalized
synchrony
um synchronization between you and your
loved ones or you
and your clients or you and your and
your
patients which would basically says that
um
to have a harmonious aligned interaction
you have to be in a like mind and
singing from the same hymn sheet
so if you are at
all um that him sheep covers all
modalities from interception from
verbal non-verbal cues but the
synchronization the alignment is still
in play
even to the level you can measure it in
terms of um
your body movements blushing for example
pupillary dilatation all of these
subliminal cues
that tell you about the state of your
embodied brain
are mutually available um and the trick
would be
i would imagine to try and synchronize
them so
um just on that mathematical basis
uh you have to put yourself in the same
state of mind as the child
in the font hope that the child will um
reciprocate by putting themselves in the
same state of mind as you
one little trick here is that the weight
the weight at which
the weight the rate at which two
couple systems converge to their common
ground
depends upon the precision or the
confidence
in the predictions of the two so if
there's an asymmetry there
you can often get a teacher or a parent
or you're a therapist
who has more if you like precise beliefs
higher in their their model that will
gent that will move towards
you know the the the less precise um
markov blanket
or or client or child
but will move less quickly than the
child moves to the parent
um and clearly you know you see that in
a natural setting just in terms of
schooling you know
it's generally the case that the teacher
is older than the child and the teacher
is more confident about what the child
knows
uh but at some point you know there is a
meeting
in the middle but it's not always in the
middle so that was a really stupid
answer
but at least it was faithful to the
mathematics
uh one final question um to to test
uh that breadth that i was posting on on
your behalf
and here is sorry
could a problem in the stability or
structuring
in the marco blanc can be thought of as
a failure or weakness of cyclic defense
and would the introduction of entropy or
dissolution
point to links with freud's ideas of the
deaf instinct
yes there are all sorts of what really
interesting ways you could take that
question in terms of structure learning
um you know
but let me focus on you know on the
freudian
um the freudian uh interpretation or
homologs here
um i think you know you if there is
part of the audience that likes this um
to understand the parallels and the
homologous and isomorphisms
between your freudian take um on
free energy and the the more
mathematical richard feynman
take on it then mark soames is your man
you know
he's you know he's written beautifully
about this and
um would normally um start the story by
noting that um freudian formulations
um inherited quite a lot from helen
holtz
so you know had uh had freud
known fireman and had you know tried to
develop helmholtz in ideas
it's more than likely his free energy
would be iso the same as
that used by people like jeffrey hinton
richard feynman
um and the interestingly when when mark
zones
goes into this in great detail he
actually
um converges on the same thing that we
were talking about before which is this
precision
um um that the the you know
i'm not sure that we can in this we
don't have time to get
to ego dissolution and the like um but
one
important um auto poetic aspect
that maintains the integrity of the
markov blanket is exactly this
attending and disattending it's
selective and appropriate
switching on and off of how the sensory
states get in and influence the internal
states and then
vicariously your actions upon the world
if that breaks
everything falls to pieces um and
that certainly is mark seaman's story um
based upon sort of
you know um a sort of
a theoretical neuropsychology based
upon um the importance of ascending
modulated neurotransmission
systems um for example dopamine and the
like
but not just dopamine all these
classical neuromodulators
because if it's the physiological
um mediation of this precision control
is via selecting selection and per
synaptic gain which is neuromodulation
so it's not surprising that a lot of
the neurochemistry of and the
pharmacology
of psychopathology fixes upon these
neuromodulators
and furthermore this is exactly
mark soda's conclusion in terms of the
um the failure uh to resolve free energy
um uh lives you know the seat of the
soul is essentially the
source of origin um of the ascending
modulated neurotransmitter systems that
are exactly there
to provide this gating attenuation
selection
uh behavior um that
um that preserves the markov blanket in
your in the sense that we've been
discussing
this is an absolutely brilliant lecture
uh
you are everything that
i have advertised you to be it is
uh obviously a revelation but a
revelation in the direction
of helping us understand sociality
helping us understand how ultimately
the brain and our
capacity to uh
create a uh create a world
that's consistent with our hypothesis
and actually uh falls into uh
a a continuum that uh we are
living every day uh in in
but as you said uh in a very strange
uh as a very strange function of time uh
it's a very strange function of time and
uh it's
uh uh to have a mind like yours that
actually can bridge
uh the uh
obstructs writings of psychoanalysts uh
with
uh the cutting-edge writings of uh
physicists and the neuroscientists in
between
and whilst maintaining an identity uh as
a
somebody who's concerned with mental
health you're a remarkable human being
you really are and we are enormously
privileged
to have had you here this evening and to
be able to benefit
from your distance so thank you so much
for joining us
thank you thank you thank you so much